Indiana University Staff Council records, 1951-1993 C399
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Staff Council records
1951-1993
1966-1993
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Staff Council
C399
3.4 cubic feet 4 boxes
The Indiana University Bloomington Staff Council was officially formed in November 1951, following authorization by the Board of Trustees. The Staff Council consisted of a body of representatives elected by and from the university employee staff. It provided University staff members with organized representation and a medium of exchange with University administration by which to advocate for staff rights and benefits. The collection consists of correspondence, agendas, minutes, policy materials, and financial information.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Administrative History
The idea to form a Staff Council at Indiana University Bloomington was first conceived by President Herman B Wells prior to 1939. The Board of Trustees preliminarily authorized a Personnel Division in 1940, under which an Employee Advisory Committee was appointed. The purpose of this division and committee was to serve as liaison for relaying problems, desires, and grievances from non-academic employees to the university administration, as well as to advise the administration concerning relevant employee welfare policies and interpret said policies to employees.
The Staff Council was officially authorized by the Board of Trustees in November 1951; it existed as a body of elected employee staff representatives democratically selected by and from non-academic staff at the university. The purpose of the Staff Council was to provide members of the university staff with a means of representative participation in the formulation of policies and solutions for problems affecting the general welfare of university staff personnel. The elected group provided a respected, organized medium of exchange of information between staff and administration which worked to promote the rights and benefits of personnel.
Prominent issues with which the Staff Council dealt include the establishment of an employee credit union (1956), employee benefits issues, grievances, leave policies, and educational grants. The Staff Council also began the Fun Frolic, which is a highly successful fundraiser at Indiana University featuring a week-long carnival with rides, games, and food offerings. The idea for the Fun Frolic was originally conceived with the intention to use proceeds toward the establishment of a Staff Council Scholarship Fund.
In 1993, the Staff Council was absorbed by the IU-CWA (Communications Workers of America), when the university Board of Trustees officially voted to acknowledge the IU-CWA as a formal union on campus.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into a single series, Administrative files. The series is further organized into two sub-series: Minutes and agendas and General files. Within the Minutes and agendas sub-series, records are arranged chronologically. Within the General files series, folders are arranged alphabetically by subject; when multiple folders exist under the same title, they are further organized chronologically or alphabetically by subtitle.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Indiana University Staff Council are organized in a single series, Administrative files. This series is further organized into two sub-series: Minutes and agendas and General files.
The first sub-series, Minutes and agendas (1966-1993), consists of minutes, agendas, attendance records, and member lists documenting business proceedings at Staff Council general meetings. Related informational documents dispersed at meetings are included in these files as well. A number of cassette tapes containing audio recordings of Staff Council meetings are included in this series, but are physically housed at the end of the collection; recordings on these tapes represent meetings for which a transcription of minutes was not identified among paper records.
The second sub-series, General files, (1951-1993) consists of a wide variety of documents related to various activities and objectives pursued by the Staff Council. General files in this series include reports, correspondence, topical documents, and on occasion, minutes, agendas, and member information. A number of documents are organized according to committees, which acted as topical subunits within the Staff Council. Also included in this series are by-laws, group chronologies, memos, year-end reports, and documents related to the Staff Council's largest annual fundraising event—the Fun Frolic. Relevant electronic files from three 5.25 inch floppy computer disks were printed out and are filed in this series as well. A number of documents from the folder entitled "Educational Grants Committee, Award Applications, 1989-1990" were identified as sensitive information; these documents are restricted to researchers and are stored at the end of the collection.
Separated Material
A number of cassette tapes documenting Staff Council meetings were discarded since transcriptions of minutes for these meetings were identified in the Minutes and agendas series. Three 5.25 inch floppy computer disks were discarded from the collection after electronic files were accessed and content printed.
Related Material
Additional records such as newsletters, annual reports, bulletins, and publications may be accessed in the Archives of Institutional Memory http://institutionalmemory.iu.edu/aim/
Acquisition Information
Accession Information: 95/040, 93/013
Provenance
Transferred from the Staff Council to the University Archives in August 1993 and 28 November 1995.
Appraisal
During processing, a number of detailed financial documents related to the Fun Frolic were removed from the collection due to their low informational value. Documents disposed of included receipts for specific purchases and documents containing information duplicated and contextualized in yearly financial reports, which are retained in the collection.
Universities and colleges --Indiana --Bloomington --Employees.; Universities and colleges --Indiana --Bloomington --Administration.; Management --Employee participation --Indiana --Bloomington.; Employee empowerment --Indiana --Bloomington.; Indiana University. Staff Council; Indiana University, Bloomington -- Employees; Indiana University, Bloomington. Staff Council -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Staff Council -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Staff Council -- History -- Sources; Indiana University. Staff Council -- Archives; Indiana University. Staff Council -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Staff Council -- History -- Sources; Indiana University -- Employees
- Administrative files, 1951-1993; undated (Box 1)
  - Minutes and agendas, 1966-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980 (Box 1)
    - 1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Audio Cassettes, 1982-1993 (Box 1)
      General
      (stored at the end of the collection, Box 4)
  - General files, 1951-1993; undated (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
      - 1966-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1969-1974 (Box 1)
      - 1974 (Box 1)
      - 1974-1978 (Box 1)
      - 1975 (Box 1)
      - 1992 (Box 2)
      - 1992-1993, (three folders) (Box 2)
      - 1993 (Box 2)
    - Agenda template, undated (Box 2)
    - Articles of Organization Committee, 1968-1972 (Box 2)
    - Authoritative Action of Board of Trustees Est. Staff Council and Joint Advisory Committee, 1951 (Box 2)
    - Authorization for the Disbursement of Funds, 5 April 1972 (Box 2)
    - Benefits (Box 2)
      - General (Box 2)
        - 1988-1992 (Box 2)
        - 1991-1993 (Box 2)
      - Survey Responses, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
      - Survey Respondents' envelopes, 1991 (Box 2)
      - Survey Results, 1988-1993 (Box 2)
    - By-laws (Box 2)
      - 1991 (Box 2)
      - undated (Box 2)
    - Conditions of Cooperation between Employee Organizations & I.U. Administration, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Council Committee Assignment & Directives (Box 2)
      - 1972 (Box 2)
      - 1974 (Box 2)
    - Document and Office Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Educational Grants Committee (Box 2)
      - Advisory Board By‑Laws, 6 October 1971 (Box 2)
      - Articles of Organization (Box 2)
        - 7 October 1970 (Box 2)
        - Revised, 6 October 1971 (Box 2)
      - Award Applications, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
        [restricted records removed]
      - Committee Reports, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Revisions, 1 December 1971 (Box 2)
    - Electronic File Printouts, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Faculty/Staff Ad Hoc Leadership Committee, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Family Leave (Box 2)
      - General, 1985-1992 (Box 2)
      - Committee (Box 2)
        - 1985-1987 (Box 2)
        - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
        - 1987-1989 (Box 2)
        - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
      - Task Force (Box 2)
        - 1984-1991 (Box 2)
        - 1988-1990 (Box 2)
        - 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Fringe Benefits Committee, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
    - Fun Frolic (Box 2)
      - General (Box 2)
        - 1970 (Box 2)
        - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
        - 1972 (Box 2)
        - 1973 (Box 2)
        - 1974 (Box 2)
        - 1975 (Box 2)
        - 1984-1987 (Box 3)
        - 1988 (Box 3)
        - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
        - 1991 (Box 3)
        - 1992 (Box 3)
        - 1993 (Box 3)
      - Finances, 1967-1993 (Box 3)
      - Weekly Reports (Box 3)
        - 1983 (Box 3)
        - 1984 (Box 3)
        - 1986 (Box 3)
        - 1989 (Box 3)
        - 1990 (Box 3)
        - 1991 (Box 3)
    - Historical File, 1966-1970 (Box 3)
    - History through 1966 (Box 3)
    - Indiana University Position Descriptions, undated (Box 3)
    - Joint Advisory Committee Proposals and action taken (Box 3)
      - 1956-1959 (Box 3)
      - 1968-1975 (Box 3)
    - Member Information (Box 3)
      - 1956-1977 (Box 3)
      - 1989 (Box 3)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Memos, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
    - Organizational By‑Laws of Joint Advisory Committee, February 1951 (Box 3)
    - Paid Parking, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Permanent Record (Box 3)
      - 1956-1966 (Box 3)
      - 1960-1967 (Box 3)
      - 1961-1971 (Box 3)
    - Proposed Organizational By-Laws on Joint Advisory Committee, 16 March 1972 (Box 3)
    - Resolution Authorizing Expenditure of Staff Council monies, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Salary Committee, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
    - Sample Election Materials, 1993 (Box 3)
    - "The Staff Council and its Achievements at Indiana University," by Kathleen Dugdale, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Staff Council President, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Staff News, 1950-1958 (Box 3)
    - Susan Osborne, Secretary, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Year End Reports (Box 3)
      - General (Box 3)
        - 1978-1984 (Box 3)
        - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
        - 1987 (Box 4)
        - 1988 (Box 4)
        - 1988-1989 (Box 4)
      - Communicator Committee, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Restricted file (Box 4)
    - Educational Grants Committee, Award Applications, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Cassette Tapes (Box 4)
    - Recordings from Staff Council Meetings (Box 4)